what up
world we are um going live here with Dr
Tommy wood here soon as soon as
old the good doctor himself comes
popping in there he goes how about that
all right
Tommy I think I did that
right these like the start of Instagram
lives are always the worst because it's
always idiots like me trying to get
things started and you're like yo can
you just get the business here Tommy
where'd you go are you
here go live with Tommy come on let's
roll
bu I think Tommy screwed it up that's
why I'm blam this all on
Tommy yo what's up Ireland I used to
live in Ireland I spent like six months
eight months no six months solid six
months in gallway it's
fantastic
Tommy what is going
on yo definitely my fall Tommy try again
dude I don't know what I did I've never
screwed this up before Tommy so things
are getting real skeptical
here says Tommy Woods is unable to
join why is Tommy wood unable to
join Tommy would able to join go live
with Dr Tommy
wood what is going on here friends maybe
Tommy's too smart they won't allow him
to do this There It
Is There He Go
hey dude you totally screwed that up
didn't
you I clicked the request button and
then everything else is you'll fall off
that D I kept hitting accept I think I
got too excited I accept like a hundred
times
how are you brother wait somebody said
who's Tommy ouch well maybe they'll find
out oh just block yourself just go ahead
and block
yourself dude Tommy the infamous Tommy
wood of of all kinds of Fame how do you
not know Tommy at this point right dope
um man I hate ding these things people
don't want to hear our chitchat so let's
get into some science um let me lay the
background down and then you're going to
be the star of the show here all right
um so uh Tommy just put out a really
nice paper um was kind enough to to get
let me be involved in it just a tiny bit
um so I wanted to talk about it because
I actually think it's uh I think it's
pretty impactful man I I know actually
some other stuff we have going on that's
going to really support that but um I
think this really was I think I tweeted
something that to the fact of that I
think I really just I really do think
this changes how we think about the
brain um and muscle and exercise in a in
a pretty big way it's not groundbreaking
I want to oversell it but it's like
pretty important I think so um wanted
you to to to walk through all that kind
of like what we found what it means why
it matters all that stuff um for the
folks that because it's a it is I'll be
honest it's a fairly technical paper so
it's a little bit tough to kind of to
kind of get through so this might be a
little bit easier for folks um so if you
could uh walk them kind of just threw
like what was the idea the Inception how
we get there and then we'll jump into
like man what do we find what do we see
or no tell let's do the opposite give
them like the Big Show right at the
gates like what was the big one or two
three things that you found um and
chrisy found and then we'll kind of walk
backwards into what all that stuff means
so uh for you that don't know Tommy is a
neuroscientist at the University of
Washington um but also heavily involved
in a lot of human performance athletes
and things like that so um full-time
neuroscientist runs a lab out there by
day but also certainly in the field as
well so that's Tommy in a
nutshell yeah plus of like a mediocrely
talented strong man we'll put it that
way like Med medoc mediocrely talented
is is the perfect description um uh yeah
so I guess the Highline is um and these
these data were from individuals in
their 60s plus right so so older
individuals uh we essentially found that
neuromuscular function which is
essentially how strong they were
relative to their body mass body
composition um and we uh in the study we
had data on leg strength like normally
it's grip strength which is like okay
but this is much better right because
it's a major muscle group so leg
strength and we found that was one of
the best predictors of cognitive
function on a standardized cognitive
test um after taking into account a
whole bunch of other stuff
like how physically active they were uh
and a whole bunch of other like risk
factors for for Dementia or cognitive
decline um the other major thing that we
found that I thought was really
interesting and kind of surprised me was
that in like to start with um I I went
in thinking like more muscle mass was
going to be associated with better
cognitive function and there have been
some other people have kind of found
something like that before we didn't
find that um and
then from there we kind of looked at why
and it's because at the population level
this is a big population data set like
1500 people um physical activity did not
correlate with muscle mass so though
people who had more muscle mass were not
getting gaining muscle mass because they
were going to the gym they were gaining
muscle mass because they were just
gaining total mass um and with total
mass comes more body fat and greater
risk of metabolic disease worse
metabolic health
um and that's interesting to me because
there have been some other studies
recently that say that people with more
muscle mass have a higher risk of
cardiovascular disease higher risk of
death and it's not because they're going
to the gym and getting super jacked and
that's increasing their risk right it's
that muscle just comes along for the rhy
when we're gaining more total mass so
that was the other thing that kind of
like fell out of this which I thought
was super important as people then try
and interpret you know somebody saying
hey there's this paper saying that
people with more muscle mass have worse
Health outcomes therefore you shouldn't
go to the gym and lift that's complete
nonsense because that's not why those
guys um or and girls people are gaining
more
muscle yeah Okay cool so uh if you're
just joining I'll feed that back to you
um around, 1500 or so people in this uh
cohort study that not directly collected
in your lab these are not hand selected
people of any kind they're just all
across the Spectrum men and women all
over the age of 60 in this analysis but
they could have been going in for this
data collection for any number of
reasons um for what at whatever site
that they went into the big finding
number one was we had leg strength um
leg was leg press right it is it was a
it was a isokinetic leg extension
kinetic leg extension okay so the
isokinetic leg extension um predicted
cognitive function which is dope right
because we hear a lot of things about oh
there's a if we go all the way back to
like yeah grip strength is is related to
overall health but that's just a proxy
for somebody being like overall healthy
right yeah which just like makes me want
to strangle somebody like quite frankly
when they say that um so let's let's go
into this one right here what when you
say that the leg strength on this
isokinetic test was correlated to
cognitive function again how do we
measure cognitive fun not how do we
measure how was it measured in these
data because we we weren't the ones that
collected it
and then walk me to like wait a minute
is there is this correlation is this
spous correlation is this direct
causation like where do we land on that
and then walk me to how could it if it
is like how is it possible your leg
strength is predicting your IQ or
whatever it so give me the whole stick
on that one yeah so I te you up for a bu
there so go
ahead so these are data from and haes
national health and nutrition
examination survey so this uh is data
that's collected in a different group of
people every year and there's supposed
to be people that represent like the
average American that's like the whole
idea so it's it's kind of like gives us
an idea of just like normal normal
people um and so the what we looked at
this ice kinetic leg strength the way we
adjusted it and kind of made it fair
right is that we looked at how strong
you were on this test relative to your
body size right because we expect
somebody who's bigger to be stronger
right we want take take that out of the
equation right so how strong are you
relative to to your size um and then the
outcome was this test called the digit
symbol substitution test which is a test
of like processing speed it's one of
these sort of General cognitive tests
that's used in like in these kinds of
studies to kind of give an idea of how
fast how good is your brain at
processing things quickly what what you
need to do is they give you a list of uh
nine different symbols and they assign
each one a number number and then you
get this big grid with numbers and you
have to write the symbol that goes with
that number underneath and you have to
do like there's 133 and you have to do
as many as you can in two minutes so you
have to do like more than one a second
so it's it's quite hard um and so that
was our main outcome uh it's sort of
like an overall um nice uh cognitive
function test and then we also adjusted
for a whole bunch of important things
education status blood pressure blood
sugar regulation some nutrient things
that are important for for risk of
cognitive decline and as well as a whole
bunch of physical activity things did
they lift did they do vigorous physical
activity and how Physically Active were
they um in their day-to-day lives so
when you take all those things into a
account you hopefully start to isolate
the effect of that muscle itself or the
ability to generates you know generate
force from like how healthy you are and
other things and this is all also when
we looked at the effect on the cognitive
function test I like I normalized it to
age as well because you just expect
function to decrease so we kind of took
all of that into account so in these
kinds of studies you can never say
something is causitive unfortunately
like epidemiology works like that but
we've taken into account a whole bunch
of things that that could be confounders
right so then you can say if you have
better neuromuscular function that was
how we kind of described it right for
your body size you're able to generate
more force with your legs which requires
you know a functioning a very
functioning nervous system from the top
all the way down um that seems to be
associated with better General cognitive
function so then from there you can
think about a number of reasons why that
might be the case and there are
certainly lots of studies that kind of
agree with this um but there's the
direct uh effects of exercise right
that's that's going to kind of play in
and we know that lots of things get
released when you exercise that can
improve brain function including lactate
and irisin and torine right that was
that was a big one that people were
talking about recently like all those
things um and then there's also some
benefit from like stimulating that
direct connection right that direct
neuromuscular stimulus from generating
work that creates the connection to the
brain so there was some other studies
randomized control trials where you take
people in their 70s you get them in a
gym and they do so um like something
really simple it's like six exercise
like machines three sets of eight three
times a week right they get stronger as
they should and their cognitive function
improves so we know from other studies
that you can intervene and you get
causation there as well so this is kind
of a nice way of saying that at a much
larger scale the more Force you can
generate with your legs in general the
better your cognitive function after
taking into account all these other
things uh that are important as well all
right so if we look at numerous other
studies uh countless studies that have
looked at direct mechanism you mentioned
a bunch of them a bunch of studies that
have done more rcts so actual training
protocols longitudinal work six weeks of
training 16 weeks of training Etc and
many of them have found direct strength
training can lead to some improvements
and cognitive function in some folks
right we take that we stack that against
what we found again just
cross-sectionally right so no
intervention in our study just looking
at how do you perform right now and how
strong are you right now right the only
way for this to be not Co
positive would be if somehow the people
in this cohort um the stronger folks
just happen to be smarter yeah so what's
the likelihood of that relative to the
of what we have on the mechanism studies
the long-term studies tal trials
everything else like that so what we can
say it's
positive
yeah counter when you posted about this
originally some like somebody said
something to the effect of like smarter
people are more likely to do exercise or
something and yeah I'm just not really
sure we want to touch that um nor is it
like this it's very possible that
there's some socioeconomic things that
play a role here we know that so
education was actually our best
predictor of cognitive function right
education is a marker of soci economic
status and then maybe you have more time
to do exercise because you're not
working for jobs to support your family
right all of that is possible yeah of
course however when you have
Interventional studies that show even in
older people like in this population
that you do some work you improve your
strength and that directly improves
cognitive function I think we can say
fairly uh confidently that at least some
of this Association is Meaningful is
this is causitive and that's um this is
kind of like a a statistical nerd thing
but even if you have observational data
if you've adjusted for all your
confounders what's left should be the
causative Association right and like
most good statisticians will will tell
you that even though like technically of
course it's not causation but what's
left should be a signal that suggests
that's the real thing I don't want to
give has to off track but the reality of
it is showing causation is so much
harder than anyone out there actually
realizes the vast majority of things you
think have been shown causation are
still just correlation like it's like
it's even mechanism studies are still
mostly correlation yeah super super
super hard to show direct causation like
almost fundamentally impossible it's
like really difficult um so we can go
there all right um that was sort of the
first major finding for those that have
again maybe just joined in can you
remind them of the second big one and
and then give me the breakdown that one
as well yes so the the second major
finding um well I guess starts with what
we describ first in the paper which is
we separated people by how much muscle
mass they have um and we were
particularly interested in those who
have low muscle mass because recent
Studies have suggested those
particularly with low muscle mass have
faster cognitive decline when we
separated like low versus normal muscle
mass we didn't see a real difference in
cognitive function there was like a
little one but it wasn't very impressive
um and so then like if we looked at well
across the entire range is like more
muscle associated with better cognitive
function on this test and it wasn't um
so then this led us down to thinking
about well why does somebody gain muscle
in the first place there are two two
main reasons broadly well you have to be
in a chloric surplus that's like in
general you right accepted but if you
just gain total mass because you eat
more than you need some of that mass is
going to be muscle right but it didn't
come from any additional work
necessarily it doesn't come with
additional neuromuscular function
because you didn't train that muscle it
just sort of is mass um and that's what
it looked like in this population those
with more muscle also had more body fat
and then with that you know both of
those things came they they were less
likely to exercise despite having more
muscle and and they had worse metabolic
Health they had worse blood sugar they
had like the men in particular had a
higher um waist circumference right so
then were talking like buiness ad poost
tissue which we know is bad for pretty
much everything um so when you when
you're looking at population studies and
there are lots now that say muscle is
good for this or bad for this you have
to think well how do we generate that
muscle and at least in this group those
who had more muscle were not gaining
muscle because they were going to the
gym so then muscle as a measure isn't
very useful right you have to look at
muscle function and that's why we had
leg strength which then kind of helps
you know make that less
complicated yeah I don't think I
necessarily need to dive too hard on
that one I feel like that one is about
as straightforward as it possibly
comes yeah it's also not
um I think it's more of an one one maybe
Inuit it that but it was nice to
actually show that directly and say no
this is like confirmed this is what
you're looking at with this data
database this is not necessarily uh
people who have again as you mentioned
accured their muscle mass via high
quality fashion so it's not necessarily
per se that that muscle is of lower
quality which it actually may be um but
then we have the performance measures to
say it probably is yeah because they're
actually like not very strong yeah yeah
when when you sort of look and you I ran
the statistical test and I looked like
well how well does all these different
physical activity measures predict
muscle um mass and it like didn't at all
like no which is just which is
completely shocking and I think that
that's again it's really important
because there are other studies out
there recently published which say more
muscle mass is associated with worse
Health outcomes and then somebody says
well because of this you know you should
get stronger but you shouldn't gain
muscle because the muscle is bad for
your health like that's just I think
it's just wrong yeah right because
nobody took into account how that muscle
was gained so I think that's kind of
dangerous telling people well because
let me go further on that one because
okay let's say in in studies like that
um that they accounted for lean mass
it's still a problem yeah right it's
still a problem because how was that
lean mass acrude
yeah as so like with that in mind like
continue on what you're saying like why
is that really dangerous potentially
maybe dangerous is too much maybe maybe
not but it's at least
misleading well I think has the
potential to be dangerous because
there's so much stuff out there that
says you shouldn't go and lift weights
because it's got It's got it gives you a
high risk of injury when actually like
traditional bodybuilding training is
super safe like for a novice to start
exercising bodybuilding training is
safer than going running in terms of
injury risk way safer way safer so
you're like people talking about injury
risk and then there's there's people
saying you know don't go to the gym and
lift weights because you'll gain muscle
and muscle is bad for your health like
based on these like
yeah exactly and so I think it is
potentially dangerous because like
people get weaker and smaller and they
lose muscle as they get older and the
best way to combat that is resistance
training and so anything that you're
doing to make people not do that I think
is potentially dangerous yeah I mean I
you know my feeling I
would um okay I want to do one more
thing here before we we let you get back
to your lovely Seattle day you probably
got some Atlas stones to go pick up or a
nature paper like 500 meter Sprints to
do on the Ry machine I'm dreading it oh
that's a mson special guaranteed it is
yep knew that one right away thanks Dr
Nelson um okay so I want to round up
with kind of uh you know what are the
additional implications or applications
for this what's this mean for the
average person um things like that and
and then before I do that though is
there anything else um you mentioned the
two big take homes but I I remember
actually like you were saying earlier
about how there was uh various
associations that popped up that were
sort of surprising I remember a couple
of them popped up and I'm like really
this is a stronger predictor like than
than muscle was to to um physical
activity right like you saying like
there was nothing in there that but then
there was Stronger prediction between
two things where I'm like geez that's
how bad this is so is there anything
else in the paper that um that the
people would be interested in that you
were particularly interested in more
importantly or anything else maybe
wasn't finding one or two but just any
other cool stuff that uh jumped the top
of mine um I think it was it was good to
kind of reaffirm all these other um risk
factors right things that we know are we
think are important and then kind of see
them all come together because usually
usually what happens when people include
these things in papers they kind of
either adjust for it or they don't and
you never like see the outcome whereas
what I like about uh our paper is I have
these graphs so you can kind of see how
everything's connected So Co so so I
think that that's a nice thing so if if
you're like a visual person then I think
the graphs are kind of cool to kind of
like see how how all things relate to
each other let me explain what that
means so you imagine a circle and all of
these variables are in a circle and
there are like a line like um like a
playground kind of like thing advice
where you know it's like a from this one
to this one you can see and Tommy did a
really cool thing or or Chris or whoever
did it and like the the thicker the
stronger the the relationship between
you the thicker the band is and it's
colors and it's kind of almost a little
bit 3D so it's a really cool visual to
just sit there and go oh I see these
variables were connected to these ones
where traditionally those would go on a
table and they would have R values and
with numbers and it would just be and
your go cross and you'd never actually
read it no because you look it just be
like this long and you're just like
asteris and numbers and zeros and you
just be like whatever so um yeah sorry
continue on but that's that's what you
mean with that really cool visual yeah I
think um no I think that's it that
that's kind of um everything else no I
think those those those are the major
takeways I don't think there's anything
else
like that's but that is a highlight all
right great anything else um that you
wna you know say about the paper or next
step or anything else that uh you know
you want to chat about here I don't want
to keep you too long uh only that you
know as we try to figure out what's
causation here like we have a a cool
project in the pipeline um just to kind
of you know throw out some teas it some
hint some teasers so so we'll actually
be looking at you know whether these
kinds of things are associated with um
improved um like real muscle quality
right that's that's your area of
expertise in ual humans as well as you
know can we detect that with blood tests
rather than having to do more invasive
things and you know how do they
associate with like important outcomes
so like in this one we had is just a
cognitive function test but how does it
affect like your risk of dementia and
other things so got a whole bunch of
stuff in the pipeline to kind of really
nail down what's what's happening here
which I think is super cool Tommy did
you just tell the world that we're
developing a blood test for muscle
quality I no I that sounds like you said
that I'm pretty sure you just said
it one of us may have just said
that I think I was vague enough and then
you just like went right out and said it
I I was clarifying and you said you
didn't say that so I was clarifying you
said you didn't say that so we'll see
we'll see um maybe amazing man where can
um obviously they can click on you and
follow you here but um your lab does a
ton of stuff mainly I wouldn't say
mainly it's not fair but I'd say the
focus of it is brain
injury and things like that but you
produce and publish a ton of stuff other
words so if people want to read your
stuff follow your work all that besides
here is there anywhere else that they
can see more of your stuff yeah uh I
have a website Dr Tommy wood.com like
all my podcasts like go on there um I
have a podcast about the brain with my
colleague Dr Josh turknet called
betterin the better brain Fitness
podcast you can find that there as well
and you have podcast
yeah I didn't know that it's fairly new
um but recommended obviously
um and uh um yeah if you like to read
papers if you're then I I put all my
papers on the website as well so there's
lots of that do you do like little blog
breakdowns or anything on that website
of your papers you just throw the paper
up there uh usually just throw the paper
up there um but that is something that I
can and should do uh when I have some
time it's a good idea well now you
should hire somebody to do that yeah
because you're not gonna have time I'll
say I have time and then never have time
yeah never gonna
Happ all right man um last last last
thing anybody you need to give a shout
out to for help on this um this paper
because obviously it wasn't just you and
I that did did this whole thing who else
needs to the credit here yeah so you
mentioned Christie S um a couple of
times she was the first author she um so
I I ran the statistics but she like
wrote a bulk of the paper with uh Ryan
garos um who's a grad student uh at udub
so between the two of them they
basically made the paper happen because
I I like playing around with data but
then actually like sitting down and
writing it out again it's hard to find
the time so so it the paper only exists
because of them and then um Ben house
and or doctors Ben house and Greg Potter
uh also co-authors and helped a lot was
sort of shaping The Narrative and making
sure it all made sense and it was you
know all the evidence behind it was good
and all that good stuff so a really
awesome team actually of people that I
love and are great including you yeah
yeah man it was it was a fun group um
that came up with lot lots of really
good insights actually on the stuff so
grad we had some students that actually
could make the paper happen
yeah and some season folks to get it
through the the finish line so um dope
man really appreciate the time as always
hopefully you all uh took something from
this um Tommy is a wealth of information
on a ton of stuff so check out his um C
his papers and then um oh actually last
one I want to ask if they have more
questions about this paper um probably
sending you DMS is not the approach I
think maybe if you've got this posted up
on Instagram somewhere um they can ask
in the comments is that the most
appropriate way or um your website or
how how would they go about that ask uh
yeah ask in the comments uh when this
gets posted uh if but if you think it's
like a a critical and important question
then I would recommend go to my website
click on the link to the podcast and the
way our podcast works is it most of the
episodes are Q&A so people submit
questions and we answer them so if
you've got a question and you think
other people interested in the answer
and we already talked about that we did
an episode about this paper as well a
couple of weeks ago um so submit a
question there and then we'll answer it
and other people can benefit hopefully
from the answer as well and what's what
uh is that episode posted of the podcast
where you cover the paper yeah it posted
either last week or the week before you
remember if you called there episode
number or anything you remember I do not
remember um but if you just go to the
better brain Fitness podcast it's was
either the last episode of the episode
before that depending on when you right
that be up shouldn't be too hard to find
and they'll cover um further breakdown
if you want to full recording this so
all right um anything else that's it
thanks man this is awesome and thanks
everybody for tuning in yeah yeah we
probably should have done some Q&A and
all that stuff but uh I like to I think
a half an hour is about like appropriate
for this um I could have done a whole
bunch more but I think this was good so
next time yeah man and if youall want
more let us know I'm happy to bring on
on Dr wood anytime here um maybe next
time we'll just do uh the live session
when you're on that rower oh we'll see
how you can answer questions yeah if if
you just well I'm not sure I will be
able to speak consider like if I think
about how terrible I felt last week um
I'm not going to be a very good guest
but you guys can watch me torch myself I
guess
thanks
see you man
bye